<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="42"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[    WOMEN AND THE VOTE: CENTENNIAL CALENDAR
]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  ]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ The Road to the Vote
On August 26, 1920, the 19th Amendment was enacted, adding one word to the Constitution—“The right of citizens of the United States to vote shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of sex.” (bold face added)
This calendar brings to life the long history of the struggle for women’s suffrage.* It honors the many hundreds of thousands of women who labored to extend the basic right to vote in the United States to women.
As we mark this centennial, we remember also that the history of women’s suffrage in the United States begins even longer ago. Some trace it to the inspiration of the women of the Seneca and other Indian nations who owned property and voted, and who influenced the thinking of the early suffragists who gathered at Seneca Falls in 1848. Some look to the US Constitution which, in 1789, left to the states the right to determine the requirements for voting.
This eighteen-month calendar extends from July 2019 to December 2020. The months from July through December 2019 contain themes and dates relating to the late 18th and 19th centuries. January through December 2020 focus on the events and people of the 20th century as well as selected dates from the 19th century.
To be certain, the enactment of the 19th Amendment in 1920 did not mark the end of the story. The work to extend suffrage continued throughout the 20th century, as constitutional amendments, laws, and court decisions added new categories of voters to the rolls (e.g., persons 18–21, residents of Washington, DC, overseas military personnel) and addressed barriers (e.g. poll taxes) that kept many women—and men—from exercising their constitutional right to vote.
The history of women’s struggle for the vote is also intertwined with struggles for the right to vote for African Americans, the poor, immigrants, Hispanics, American Indians, and others. It has been a history marked by successes and setbacks, cooperation as well as conflict, sexism as well as racism.
This story of universal suffrage is still unfolding. Despite progress, voter suppression efforts are alive and well, interfering with the ability of all citizens to exercise their fundamental right to vote.
As suffragist Crystal Eastman reminded her sisters following the passage of the 19th Amendment, “Now we can begin.” * From the Latin word suffragium, meaning the right to vote.
 ]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                     MOTT Lucretia Mott
Abolitionist & suffragist
Organizes Seneca Falls Convention
President, AERA
STANTON Elizabeth Cady Stanton
Abolitionist & suffragist
Organizes Seneca Falls Convention
Co-founds AERA Co-founds NWSA Co-founds NAWSA
ANTHONY Susan B. Anthony
Temperance advocate, suffragist, & abolitionist
Co-founds Women’s State Temperance Society
Co-founds AERA Co-founds NWSA Co-founds NAWSA
TRUTH Sojourner Truth
Abolitionist & suffragist
Addresses 1851, 1853 Woman’s RIghts Conventions
Addresses AERA (1867) Member, AWSA
STONE Lucy Stone
Abolitionist & suffragist Co-founds AERA
Co-founds AWSA with husband Henry Blackwell
BLACKWELL Alice Stone Blackwell
Daughter of Stone & Blackwell
Reconciles NWSA & AWSA
CATT Carrie Chapman Catt
President, NAWSA
Founds League of Women Voters
SHAW Anna Howard Shaw
Minister, medical doctor, activist
Member, NWSA President, NAWSA
PAUL Alice Paul
Adapts tactics from UK
Leads NAWSA Congressional Committee
Founds Congressional Union
Founds NWP
                    National Woman Suffrage Association (NWSA) (1869-1890)
Opposes 15th Amendment without inclusion of woman suffrage
             First Woman’s Rights Convention held at Seneca falls (1848)
American Equal Rights Association
(AERA) (1866-1869) -- dedicated to suffrage for all American citizens
Suffragists split into two major organizations over inclusion of women in the 15th Amendment (1869)
Women’s suffrage movement division reconciled
National American Woman Suffrage Association (NAWSA) (1890-1920)
Focuses on adoption of women’s suffrage state by state
League of Women Voters (1920-present)
            Women’s suffragists & abolitionists collaborate
American Woman Suffrage Association (AWSA) (1869-1890)
Supports 15th Amendment despite exclusion of woman suffrage
Suffragists shift focus to federal amendment
           Women’s rights conventions held across U.S.
Suffrage activity suspended
National Woman’s Party Founded (NWP) (1916-present)
      Civil War (1861-1865)
Passage of the 14th Amendment
Passage of the 15th Amendment
Enactment of the 19th Amendment
    1848 1861 1865 1866 1868 1869 1870 1890 1913 1916 1920
   ]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  JULY 2019
The 1800s give rise to activism addressing emancipation, suffrage and other basic human rights. In Seneca Falls, at the First Woman’s Rights Convention, organizers Mott and Stanton and attendees — including Frederick Douglass, a lifelong defender of women’s rights (below)––sign the Declaration of Sentiments promoting women’s rights. In the following years, activists convene and form multiple national organizations to press for suffrage over the next 70 years.
 SUNDAY
 MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
    1
   2
1776 Blacks and women with property can vote in NJ; reversed in 1807.
 3
   4 IndependenceDay
1876 Declaration of the Rights of the Women of the US proclaimed.
  5
  6
   7
 8
   9
1868 14th Amendment is ratified extending citizenship and rights.
 10
1890 US admits Wyoming as a state, where women already have the vote.
   11
  12
  13
1848 Informal meeting is held to plan convention to discuss women’s rights.
   14
15
  16
17
  18
 19
1848 First Woman’s Rights Convention opens at Seneca Falls, NY.
 20
 21
1896 National Association of Colored Women (NACW) is founded.
 22
 23
 24
 25
  26
  27
  28
 29
  30
 31
 We hold these truths to be self-evident; that all men and women are created equal; that they are endowed by their Creator with certain inalienable rights; that among these are life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness .... Now, in view of this entire disfranchisement of one-half the people of this country ... we insist that they have immediate admission to all the rights and privileges which belong to them as citizens of these United States.
Declaration of Sentiments, July 20, 1848
      ]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[               ]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  AUGUST 2019
Throughout the 1800s, pioneering women suffragists break through traditional barriers to speak, write, and publish on suffrage and other issues including slavery and temperance: (clockwise) Amelia Bloomer owns and edits The Lily; Susan B. Anthony and Elizabeth Cady Stanton launch The Revolution; Frances Harper is a poet, author, orator, and co-founder of AWSA; Lucy Stone, a noted orator, founds The Woman’s Journal; Mary Ann Shadd Cary is the first black woman publisher (The Provincial Freeman); and Ida B. Wells is an acclaimed journalist, publisher, and activist. Josephine Ruffin (below) publishes The Woman’s Era.
 SUNDAY
 MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
        1
1895 Josephine Ruffin (left) calls for a “new era” for the colored women of America.
  2
1848 Abigail Bush chairs Adjourned Convention in Rochester, NY.
  3
   4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
 10
 11
 12
  13
  14
  15
1855 Susan B. Anthony opens Convention to discuss woman’s right to suffrage at Saratoga Springs.
  16
  17
 18
 19
  20
  21
  22
  23
  24
1848 Lucretia Mott writes to the Liberator about her visit to the Seneca Nation.
 25
 26
 27
  28
   29
   30
1835 Abolitionist Sara Grimke publishes letter on Boston slavery riot.
   31
       ]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  ]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  SEPTEMBER 2019
The 15th Amendment, ratified on February 3, 1870, prohibits federal and state governments from denying citizens the right to vote due to “race, color, or previous condition of servitude.” Its passage is followed by Reconstruction and a period of voter suppression that uses poll taxes, literacy tests, violence, and other means. It takes nearly 100 years for poll taxes to be prohibited by the 24th Amendment and the sweeping reforms of the Voting Rights Act of 1965 that break down many state and local legal barriers to voting by African American men and women (below).
 SUNDAY
 MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
  1
1853 Suffragists
attend Whole World’s Temperance Convention but are expelled.
  2 Labor Day
  3
  4
  5
  6
1870 First woman votes in Territory of Wyoming.
  7
   8
 9
 10
 11
 12
1882 American Woman Suffrage Association (AWSA) holds annual Convention in Omaha, Nebraska.
 13
 14
 15
  16
  17
1789 US Constitution signed. States keep authority to decide who can vote.
   18
   19
   20
  21
   22
 23
 24
1875 Matilda Gage
writes about Five Nations confederacy where women “exercise power in peace and war.”
  25
  26
1882 National Woman Suffrage Association (NWSA) holds annual convention in
Omaha, Nebraska.
 27
 28
 29
 30
            ]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[    ]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  OCTOBER 2019
NAACP’s magazine, The Crisis, a strong supporter of women’s suffrage, commemorates a meeting 50 years earlier between Sojourner Truth and President Lincoln in a special 1915 edition on suffrage (above). Sojourner Truth, born a slave, is a skilled orator, passionate abolitionist, and proponent of suffrage for women and black men. Harriet Tubman (below), also born a slave, supports hundreds escaping north from slavery, serves as a scout, spy, and nurse for the Union Army, and is an advocate for women’s suffrage and rights in her later years.
 SUNDAY
MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
   1
   2
  3
  4
  5
  6
 7
8
  9
 10
1866 Elizabeth Stanton runs for NY Congress. Loses in November.
 11
 12
 13
 14 Columbus Day
 15
1872 Virginia Louisa Minor tries to register to vote under 14th Amendment.
   16
  17
 18
 19
 20
 21
 22
 23
1850 First National Woman’s Rights Convention opens in Worcester, MA.
 24
 25
 26
 27
 28
 29
1864 Sojourner Truth visits President Lincoln in the White House (right).
  30
 31
         ]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  ]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  NOVEMBER 2019
An 1869 depiction of universal suffrage by Thomas Nast in Harper’s Weekly reflects the inclusive vision of many 19th century abolitionists and suffragists who are working to abolish slavery and to promote universalsuffrage.TheAERA,forexample,isfoundedin1866 “tosecureEqualRightstoallAmerican citizens, especially the right of suffrage, irrespective of race, color, or sex.” The 1869 Thanksgiving Proclamation reflects the hopefulness and optimism following the Civil War.
 SUNDAY
MONDAY
TUESDAY
WEDNESDAY
THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
 The year which is drawing to a close has been free from pestilence; health has prevailed throughout the land; abundant crops reward the labors of the husbandman; commerce and manufactures have successfully prosecuted their peaceful paths; the mines and forests have yielded liberally; the nation has increased in wealth and in strength; peace has prevailed, and its blessings have advanced every interest of the people in every part of the Union; harmony and fraternal intercourse restored are obliterating the marks of past conflict and estrangement; burdens have been lightened; means have been increased; civil and religious liberty are secured to every inhabitant of the land, whose soil is trod by none but freemen.
Thanksgiving Day Proclamation, 1869
  1
  2
  3
1896 Women gain vote in Idaho, the fourth state with suffrage.
 4
  51872 Susan B. Anthony casts a vote for President.
1867 Kansas’s proposal to grant vote to women and blacks is defeated.
  6
  7
1893 Colorado is first state to pass women’s suffrage at polls.
 8
 9
 10
  11 Veterans Day
   12
   13
   14
   15
   16
   17
 18
1872 Susan B. Anthony arrested for casting a vote for President.
 19 1861 Julia Ward Howe writes “Battle Hymn of the Republic.”
1868 NJ women bring own ballot box to vote for president.
 20
1874 Woman’s Christian Temperance Union concludes first meeting.
 21
 22
 23
 24
 25
 26
  27
   28 ThanksgivingDay
   29
   30
      ]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  ]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  DECEMBER 2019
In a 1915 illustrative map in the journal, Puck, Lady Liberty wears a cape with “Votes for Women.” She strides across the US from the West, where women already have the vote, toward the outstretched hands of women in the East and South who still have no vote. Suffragists use maps and data (below) to track and show progress.
 SUNDAY
 MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
  1
  2
  3
  4
  5
  6
  7
1868 Universal suffrage amendment is introduced in Senate. Never voted on.
   8
 9
 10
1869 Women gain right to vote in Wyoming Territory.
 11
 12
 13
 14
 15
  16
  17
  18
  19
  20
  21
   22
 23
1873 Women begin temperance movement in Ohio.
 24
 25 Christmas Day
  26
  27
  28
 29
 30
 31
            ]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  ]]></page><page Index="17" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  JANUARY 2020
Borrowing tactics from more militant British “Suffragettes,” the National Woman’s Party, led by Alice Paul and Lucy Burns, brings the protest to the White House gates. Throughout a 21⁄2-year-long vigil, thousands of women stand as Silent Sentinels, light a watchfire (below), and hold signs challenging the President to support suffrage and endorse a constitutional amendment. The vigil only ends on June 4, 1919, when Congress passes a proposed amendment to extend the vote to women and focus shifts from the federal level to the states to ensure ratification.
 SUNDAY
MONDAY
TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
    1 NewYear’sDay
1849 Amelia Bloomer founds
The Lily.
1919 National Woman’s Party lights first “Watchfire of Freedom.”
   2
  3
  4
1896 Utah gains statehood; Utah women regain right to vote.
  5
 6
  7
8
  9
1882 Senate forms Select Committee on Woman Suffrage.
 10 1878Firstfederal woman suffrage amendment introduced in Senate.
1918 Woman suffrage amendment passes House (274 to 136).
 11
 12
  13
1913 Black sorority Delta Sigma Theta founded (see Feb for emblem).
   14
  15
    16
1919 States ratify 18th Amendment prohibiting “intoxicating liquors.”
   17
   18
   19
1920 American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) is founded.
 20 MartinLutherKing,Jr. Day
 21
22
  23
 24
 25
1887 Woman suffrage amendment loses in Senate (16-34).
 26
 27
 28
 29
    30
   31
          ]]></page><page Index="18" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[      ]]></page><page Index="19" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  FEBRUARY 2020
In the late 19th century, black women found clubs focusing on the welfare of their communities, education, and other social issues including suffrage. In 1896, two major clubs merge to form the first truly national organization of black women — the National Association of Colored Women (NACW). Mary Church Terrell is its first President (above) and “Lifting As We Climb” its motto. With the leadership of Harriet Tubman (2nd row, 6th from right), Margaret Washington, Fannie Barrier Williams and others, the NACW grows to 50,000 members and 1,000 clubs nationwide by 1914. Mary McLeod Bethune is elected President in 1924.
 SUNDAY
MONDAY
TUESDAY
WEDNESDAY
THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
          1
  2
 3
1870 15th Amendment is ratified.
 4
1925 Hearings on ERA held by House Judiciary Committee.
   5
  6
 7
 8
 9
 10
1919 Senate defeats federal woman’s suffrage amendment by one vote.
 11
   12
1909 National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) is founded.
  13
1893 Ida B. Wells details horrors of lynching to white audience in Boston.
  14 1870Firstwoman votes in Utah.
1912 Women gain vote in Arizona.
1920 Catt founds League of Women Voters.
  15
1906 Susan B. Anthony’s 86th birthday: “Failure is impossible.”
 16
 17 Washington’s Birthday
 18
1890 NWSA & AWSA merge to become NAWSA.
   19
  20
  21
  22
 23
 24
 25
  26
   27
1922 Supreme Court upholds 19th Amendment as constitutional.
   28
   29
       ]]></page><page Index="20" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  ]]></page><page Index="21" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  MARCH 2020
To reinvigorate the suffrage movement, the National American Woman Suffrage Association, under Alice Paul’s leadership, organizes the first political parade in Washington, DC, on the day before President Wilson’s inauguration. Thousands of women from across the country march, including state delegates, teachers, women who hike from New York, and representatives from other countries. As a protest against the exclusion of black women, Ida B. Wells joins the Illinois delegation (below, right). Terrell represents NACW and marches with Delta Sigma Theta in their first public act. In 1953, at the age of 90, she marches with pickets to integrate Washington. DC lunch counters.
 SUNDAY
 MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
  1
  2
 3
1913 Inez Milholland Boissevain leads suffrage parade in Washington, DC.
   4
  5
  6
  7
   8
 9
10
  11
 12
 13
 14
 15
  16
  17
  18
  19
1914 Suffrage Amendment loses in Senate.
  20
  21
   22 1972 ERA Amendment approved by Senate; ratification by states begins.
1984 Mississippi is last state to ratify 19th Amendment, 64 years later.
 23
24
1919 Catt proposes League of Women Voters to “finish the fight.”
  25
1911 Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire highlights workplace safety issues.
  26
  27
  28
  29
1961 23rd Amendment: DC residents can vote in presidential elections.
 30
 31
1776 Abigail Adams exhorts husband John to “Remember the ladies.”
          ]]></page><page Index="22" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  ]]></page><page Index="23" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  APRIL 2020
Suffragists criss-cross the country by train going to conventions and mobilizing voters in support of suffrage. In 1909, a group travels to Seattle for a NAWSA convention. The Congressional Union sends envoys to mobilize western women voters to support the 19th Amendment (route map below). Following the Senate’s defeat of the proposed amendment in February 2019, suffragists launch a “final push.” To gain national attention, they wear the garb of the Occoquan prisoners and mount a train tour
th thatisdubbed“ThePrisonSpecial.”Fourmonthslater,onJune4,1919,theSenatepassesthe19 Amendment.
 SUNDAY
 MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
      1
  2
1917 Jeanette Rankin is sworn in as the first female representative in the House.
 3
   4
   5
 6
1917 US enters World War I.
 7
 8
 9
1916 Suffrage Special train leaves DC for a five-week tour.
1865 Civil War ends.
10
  11
 12
1861 Civil War begins; suffrage activity suspended.
  13
   14
1910 Alice Paul encourages NAWSA to adopt more militant approaches used by British activists.
   15
   16
1921 President Harding meets with NWP members to discuss Equal Rights Bill.
  17
    18
   19
1929 Literate Puerto Rican women gain vote after years of activism.
 20
 21
 22
 23
24
  25
 26
 27
 28
  29
   30
               ]]></page><page Index="24" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  ]]></page><page Index="25" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  MAY 2020
Between 1911 and 1917, suffragists march in NYC in multiple parades as the campaign for suffrage also expands across the country. Dr. Anna Shaw (above, left) and Carrie Chapman Catt (above, right), founder of the League of Women Voters, lead marchers in a suffrage parade on October 27, 1917, to showcase a petition bearing more than one million women’s signatures.
 SUNDAY
MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
          1
  2
1914 Suffrage parades and meetings are held nationwide.
  3
 4
 5
 6
1911 3,000 women march for women’s suffrage in New York City.
 7
 8
 9 1865SojournerTruth addresses AERA, sings, “We are going home.”
1914 Mass meeting and march to Capitol by Congressional Union for Woman Suffrage.
 10
1886 Frances Harper: “White women speak of rights; I speak of wrongs.”
 11
  12
  13
  14
  15
  16
 17
 18
  19
  20
  21
1919 House passes the proposed suffrage amendment (304 to 89).
  22
  23
 24
31
 25 Memorial Day
 26
  27
   28
   29
1851 Sojourner Truth delivers “Ain’t I a Woman” speech in Ohio.
   30
      ]]></page><page Index="26" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  ]]></page><page Index="27" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  JUNE 2020
The origins of the National Woman’s Party (NWP) date from 1912, when Alice Paul and Lucy Burns, young Americans schooled in the militant tactics of British suffragism, are appointed to NAWSA’s Congressional Committee. They inject more militancy into the American campaign and shift attention away from state voting rights toward a federal suffrage amendment. The NWP is formed at a June 5–7, 1916, meeting of the Congressional Union in Chicago. Note: NAWSA badge from 1905 (below) honors Sacagawea as first woman to vote in America.
 SUNDAY
 MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
     1
  2
1924 Indian Citizenship Act provides vote to US-born American Indians.
  3
  4
1919 Following 41 years of debate, Senate passes woman suffrage amendment and ratification begins.
  5
1916 National Woman’s Party founded in Chicago.
  6
   7
 8
 9
 10
1919 Wisconsin, Illinois, and Michigan are first states to ratify 19th Amendment.
 11
 12
 13
 14
1878 Senate receives 30,000 signatures for woman suffrage amendment; postpones consideration “indefinitely.”
 15
 16
1919 Kansas, New York, and Ohio ratify
19th Amendment.
 17
  18
  19
 20
 21
 22
 23
 24
 25
 26
 27
1952 McCarran-Walter Act lets Asians become citizens and vote.
 28
 29
1909 Suffrage Special arrives in Seattle for NAWSA convention.
 30
               ]]></page><page Index="28" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[   ]]></page><page Index="29" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  JULY 2020
Many of the thousands of suffragists who picket at the White House and elsewhere are harassed, insulted, arrested, and otherwise unjustly treated by local and federal authorities. Lucy Burns (below, center) is among those who are imprisoned and force-fed when she goes on a hunger strike. On November 14, 1917, in what is known as the “Night of Terror,” many suffragists are brutally tortured and abused in the jail where they are being held.
 SUNDAY
MONDAY
TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
      1
1971 26th Amendment: Congress lowers the voting age to 18.
  2
1919 Iowa ratifies the 19th Amendment as 10th state.
  3
1919 Missouri ratifies the 19th Amendment as 11th state.
  4 Independence Day
  5
 6
  7
 8
 9
 10
 11
 12
 13
1913 Suffragists bring petition with 75,000 signatures to Senate.
  14
  15
  16
  17
  18
 19
 20
1923 Draft of ERA presented at 75th Anniversary of Seneca Falls convention.
  21
  22
  23
  24
  25
 26
 27
 28
1919 Arkansas is 12th state to ratify the 19th Amendment.
  29
   30
   31
1913 In “Siege of
the Senate,” suffragists deliver 75,000 signatures
by motorcar.
          ]]></page><page Index="30" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  ]]></page><page Index="31" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  AUGUST 2020
After the Tennessee legislature passes the 19th Amendment by a single vote, Alice Paul, on the balcony of the headquarters of the National Woman’s Party in DC, unfurls a banner with 36 stars; the 36th star represents Tennessee, the 36th and last state necessary for ratification. According to Carrie Catt, it had taken pauseless campaigning with “56 referenda to male voters; 480 campaigns to legislatures; 47 campaigns to state constitutional conventions for women’s suffrage; 277 campaigns re-suffrage in state party platforms; and 19 campaigns with 19 successive Congresses.”
 SUNDAY
MONDAY
TUESDAY
WEDNESDAY
THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
        1
  2
1919 Montana and Nebraska ratify 19th Amendment.
 3
  4
  5
  6
1965 Voting Rights
Act prohibits racial discrimination in voting.
 7
 8
 9
 10
  11
  12
  13
  14
  15
1918 After being arrested and sentenced to time
in workhouse, Lafayette Park protesters begin hunger strike.
 16
 17
  18
1920 Tennessee ratifies 19th Amendment by a single vote.
  19
  20
  21
  22
 23
30
 24
31
 25
  26
1920 19th Amendment signed into law—women can now vote!
   27
   28
1986 Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act passed.
   29
       ]]></page><page Index="32" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[              ]]></page><page Index="33" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  SEPTEMBER 2020
In the early years of the 20th century, women such as Emily Newell Blair (top, left), Adella Hunt Logan (top, right), Alice Paul (bottom, left), and Nina Allender (bottom, right) continue to write and draw in a variety of national and local journals including The Suffragist, Missouri Woman, and the re-named Woman’s Journal and Suffragist News. The passage of the 19th Amendment is covered on the front pages of suffragist papers, such as The Woman Citizen, as well as national and local newspapers.
 SUNDAY
 MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
     1
   2
  3
 4
   5
   6
 7 Labor Day
8
1919 Minnesota ratifies 19th Amendment.
  9
 10
1919 New Hampshire ratifies 19th Amendment.
11
  12
 13
 14 1915 18,000-foot- long suffrage petition reaches a half-million signatures.
1917 Senator Andrieus Jones visits Occoquan Workhouse prisoners.
 15
   16
  17
 18
 19
 20
 21
 22
 23
 24
 25
1915 Suffragists Sara Bard Field and Frances Joliffe leave San Francisco by automobile.
  26
  27
 28
 29
  30
1918 President Wilson addresses Senate in support of women’s suffrage.
          ]]></page><page Index="34" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[              ]]></page><page Index="35" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  OCTOBER 2020
Cars are central to the final push for the 19th Amendment. Women drive cars in parades and use them as platforms to give speeches at rallies and demonstrations. Cars are a symbol of women’s “modernity, independence, and mobility.” Two women, Nell Richardson and Alice Burke (below), drive from New York to San Francisco drumming up support for suffrage.
 SUNDAY
MONDAY
TUESDAY
WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
     1
1918 Suffrage amendment fails in Senate by two votes.
  2
  3
  4
 5
 6
   7
1918 NWP starts to picket the US Capitol.
 8
 9
 10
1911 Women gain vote in California.
 11
 12 ColumbusDay
1971 House passes Equal Rights Amendment.
 13
   14
  15
  16
  17
 18
 19
 20
1917 Alice Paul is arrested protesting in front of White House.
   21
  22
1917 Alice Paul sentenced to 7 months in Occoquan Workhouse.
  23
1915 25,000 women march up Fifth Avenue in New York.
  24
 25
 26
 27
1917 20,000 women march and campaign statewide in final push before New York’s November vote on suffrage.
  28
   29
   30
   31
      ]]></page><page Index="36" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[    ]]></page><page Index="37" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  NOVEMBER 2020
On November 2, 1920, for the first time, women nationwide are entitled to vote in the 34th presidential election: 8 million women vote.
 SUNDAY
 MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
  1
  2
1920 8 million women vote across the US.
  3
1914 Women gain the right to vote in Montana and Nevada.
  4
  5
1912 Women gain the right to vote in Arizona, Kansas, and Oregon.
  6
1917 Women gain the right to vote in New York.
  7
   8
1910 Women gain the right to vote in Washington State.
 9
 10
 11 VeteransDay 1918 World War I ends.
 12
 13
 14
1917 “Night of Terror:” Workhouse guards brutalize Lucy Burns and other suffragists.
 15
 16
 17
  18
  19
  20
 21
 22
 23
 24
 25
 26 ThanksgivingDay
 27
 28
 29
 30
                  ]]></page><page Index="38" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[    ]]></page><page Index="39" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  DECEMBER 2020
Even with the successful passage of the 19th Amendment, suffragists are clear that they have not accomplished everything needed for women to be full participants in American democracy. Alice Paul immediately begins work on the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA). Even 100 years later, Virginia fails in 2019 by a single vote to pass the ERA as the 38th state needed for ratification; many women and men face continuing forms of voter suppression; and, as recently as 2018, 37.5 million women who are citizens are not registered to vote. The work continues.
 SUNDAY
MONDAY
 TUESDAY
 WEDNESDAY
 THURSDAY
 FRIDAY
SATURDAY
 “There is a danger that because of a great victory women will believe their whole struggle for independence ended. They have still far to go.” –Alice Paul, 1921
  1
  2
 3
   4
  5
  6 1915envoyof2,000 suffragists march to
US Capitol.
1937 Breedlove v. Suttles upholds the constitutionality of the poll tax.
 7
1915 8-day National Convention of CU takes place in Washington, DC.
 8
 9
10
  11
 12
 13
1923 Equal Rights Amendment is introduced in Congress.
 14
  15
  16
1918 After NWP Conference, 300 women burn President Wilson’s speeches.
 17
1943 Chinese Exclusion Act repealed.
 18
 19
 20
 21
  22
  23
 24
 25 Christmas Day
  26
  27
 28
 29
 30
 31
       Aim your phone at it and you can register to vote anywhere in the US!!!
17762020!!
]]></page><page Index="40" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[  Acknowledgements
Ann Lewis and Mike Sponder Women’s Suffrage Collection National Woman’s Party, Belmont-Paul Equality National Monument Elizabeth Cady Stanton Trust, Coline Jenkins
Library of Congress
National Association of Colored Women’s Clubs
The Frick Pittsburgh
Vote.org
Editors
Suzanne Finney Pamela R. Johnson PhD
Designer
Renée Winfield
Contributors
Gretchen Bloom, Ina Descartes, Anna Fierst, Patricia Fitzgerald, Jo Freeman PhD JD, Katherin Golitzen, Pege Gilgannon, Judy Hubbard, Marisha Kirtane, Karen O’Connor PhD JD, Rosalyn Overstreet Gonzalez, Esquire, Megan Rodriguez, Carol L. Rogers PhD, Macquarie Simon, Loulou Sloss, and Arthelda Busch Williams EdD
  ]]></page><page Index="41" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[    ]]></page><page Index="42" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[                    MOTT
Lucretia Mott
Abolitionist & suffragist Organizes Seneca Falls Convention
President, AERA
STANTON
Elizabeth Cady Stanton
Abolitionist & suffragist Organizes Seneca Falls Convention
Co-founds AERA Co-founds NWSA Co-founds NAWSA
ANTHONY
Susan B. Anthony
Temperance advocate, suffragist, & abolitionist Co-founds Women’s State Temperance Society Co-founds AERA Co-founds NWSA Co-founds NAWSA
TRUTH
Sojourner Truth
Abolitionist & suffragist Addresses 1851, 1853 Woman’s RIghts CAdodnrveesnsteiosnAsERA (1867) Member, AWSA
Patshsea1g4ethof Amendment
1868
STONE
Lucy Stone
Abolitionist & suffragist Co-founds AERA Co-founds AWSA with hBulascbkawnedllHenry
1869
BLACKWELL
Alice Stone Blackwell
Daughter of
Stone & Blackwell Reconciles NWSA & AWSA
Patshsea1g5ethof Amendment
1870
CATT
Carrie Chapman Catt
President, NAWSA Founds League of Women Voters
1890
SHAW
Anna Howard Shaw
Minister, medical doctor, activist Member, NWSA President, NAWSA
PAUL
Alice Paul
Adapts tactics from UK Leads NAWSA Congressional CFoumnmdsitCteoengressional Union
Founds NWP
    FCiorsntvWenotmionanh’selRdiagthts Seneca falls (1848)
  aWbolmitieon’istsucfforlalagbisotrsa&te Womehne’sldraigchrtosscsoUn.vSe.ntions
1848 1861
1865 1866
Suffrage activity suspended
Civil War (1861-1865)
Samufefrnadgmisetsnst hift focus to federal
N(NaWtioPn)a(1l 9W1o6m-parens’senPta)rty Founded
Enathctem1e9ntht of
Amendment 1913 1916 1920
N
AmeriAcsasnoEcqiautaiolnRights S (AsEuRffrAa)g(e1f8o6r6a-l1l 8A6m9e) r-i-cadnedciictiaztendsto
OaptpiosneaslW15othmAamneSndumffreangtewAithsosuotciinactliuosni
minucafljuforsarigoinrsgtosafnswipzolaitmtionentnositonwvtoehre 15th Amendment (1869)
ASumpeproirctsan15Wth AomeandSmuefnftradegsepAitesseoxcluiastioionno(fAwWomSaAn) s(1u8ffr6a9g-e1890)
o(nNoWfSwAo)m(a1n86s9u-f1fr8a9
g0e)
Womenm’sosvuefmfraegnet division reconciled
National Amer(NicAaWn WSAo)m(1a8n9S0u-1f9fr2a0g)e Association L
Focuses on adoption of women’s suffrage state by state
W(1e9oa2mg0ue-penroeVfsoetenrts)
                                          Check to see if you are registered to vote! Point your camera at the pattern above and press. Or go to vote.org to check your status or register.
Published by the WNDC Educational Foundation
1776-2020!!
 Aim your phone at it and you can register to vote anywhere in the US!!!
www.WNDCEducationalFoundation.org
© Copyright 2019. WNDC Educational Foundation, a not-for-profit, section 501(c)(3)
]]></page></pages></Search>